Stay seated.
Don't do that please.
Give it up. Thank you.
See you.
- Thank you.
- You're welcome. Have a good day.
963 to Base.
Clifton Road dropped. Over.
Copy that, 963.
Fight! Fight!
Bye. Thanks.
You're welcome.
Hey. Quit messing with the windows please.
963 to Base.
All kids dropped. Over.
Copy that, 963.
Meanwhile,
the Mavericks broke their losing streak
with a resounding win
over the Wizards, 119-100.
Weather today, sunny, dry and windy.
Still no sign of an end
to this record dry spell.
Day 210 without a drop of rain.
And don't forget,
there's a Red Flag Wildfire Warning
in effect for Butte County
and surrounding areas through Friday,
with the possibility
of electrical shutoffs.
Looking ahead, you guessed it,
even more dry and windy weather
in store tomorrow with gusts
anywhere from 60 to 80 miles per hour.
In local news, after going eight--
Hey, what do I need for Billie Park?
Who can I get?
Try 190.
Great.
- This is Base. You there, Mack?
- What do you need?
Yeah. Can you do the Billie Park
pickup today? Phil's bailed.
- No problem, Chief.
- Thank you so much.
Base clear. Hey, Kevin.
- Yeah?
- Got those time sheets for me?
No. I'll, uh…
I'll make sure to bring 'em in tomorrow.
Okay. And the foreman says
you're behind on maintenance.
That's your responsibility.
- Yeah?
- Copy that.
Hi there. This is Ruby
at the Unified Transportation District.
Yeah.
Hey, boss.
Yeah. Just a sec.
Hey there. It's Ruby down at the bus yard.
Uh, I was just wondering if you knew
anything about the PG&E shutoffs.
We got a Red Flag Warning, so I just need
to know if the schools are gonna close.
Yeah, I'll hold.
- What's up? Mmm.
- About those additional shifts.
Um…  …I could
sure use the extra this month.
Uh, I've got my dad's medical bills.
I'm taking care of my mom.
My ex is home.
Uh, so it's a bit of a sticky time.
Yeah, I just don't have
anything for you, Kevin.
Well, boss,
when I signed up, you said…
I said maybe, yeah?
And people that have been here longer,
the guys that have seniority,
- they get first pick of overtime shifts.
- Hey, buddy. Hurry it up.
- Mind your business, old man.
- Hey.
If anything comes up, I'll let you know.
Do you copy?
Copy.
- I'm not staying on the line.
Richard, I am so sorry.
It's okay.
- Yeah.
- Hey, Kevin. It's Dr. Everett.
We got Elvis's X-rays back.
- Bad news, I'm afraid.
- His cancer has spread.
I think it's time.
All right, doc. I'll…
I'll bring him by tonight. Thank you.
Hey, bud. How you doing?
Come here. Come here, buddy.
Come here.
Come here. Come here,
come here, come here.
Hop up.
- I got ya. I got ya. I got ya.
You want
a burger for dinner, buddy?
Huh?
I got you, buddy.
- Hey, Ma.
- Hey, Kevin.
- There you go, buddy.
There you go.
Shaun's home.
- Home?
- He said he was sick.
And you believed him?
All I need is the school board
on my ass now.
You okay?
Struggling, Ma.
I can't seem to catch a break.
So, what, back to Reno?
No.
I just…
I just can't make it here.
Well, you know your dad did.
Yeah. Well, I'm not him, remember?
School's important, bud.
Wasn't important to you.
Lay down.
Buddy…  …that's different.
- Dropped out, yeah?
- Yeah. I did.
We got pregnant. I ha… I had to.
- So it's my fault then?
- No.
It's not your fault, bud.
I just…
I don't want you making my mistakes.
That… Tha-That's all.
Come on. U-Unpack your bags.
Put your stuff in a proper drawer.
I'm off this Saturday.
You and I can do something this weekend.
I'm good.
I don't feel well.
Talk to me, buddy.
Talk to me.
You think I wanna be here? Huh?
You think I wanna be here
taking care of your grandma?
All right. But you… Don't…
Hey. Listen to me.
I don't have a choice. You do.
Dad, it's not fair
that I have to change my life.
Grow up!
Wait till you gotta pay bills!
Wait till you got a job
that's a dead-end motherfucker,
that doesn't pay, and you can't quit.
You know what it's like
to not have some pity party?
You know what it's like not
- to have something to look forward to?
- Yeah, I do.
- Well, how the fuck do you know?
- I know because of you.
This is my fault now?
Of course it's not, Dad.
Never is.
You know, I fucking hate you.
I wish you were dead!
Okay, buddy.
- Good boy.
- You had him long?
Since he was a puppy.
- Do you wanna hold him?
- Yeah.
It's okay, buddy.
It's okay.
…weather now,
and it's another dry and windy day
in Paradise with gusts in the canyon
up to 80 miles per hour.
That Red Flag Wildfire Warning is
still in effect, so be careful out there,
and be sure to report
any signs of smoke or fire immediately.
Looking at tomorrow--
Hey, guys.
We got a couple of downed trees
in these winds on Roe Road.
That's Roe Road,
so just… Watch out for power lines too.
All right. Base out.
- Hey, Kevin.
- Hey, boss.
Mechanic's in this morning,
so I want you to get 963 serviced
when you get back.
Well past three K limit.
I want you to stick around,
watch him do his checks.
It's gonna take a couple hours,
but it's stuff you gotta know.
- All right?
- Copy that, boss.
There's yesterday's time sheet.
Thank you, sir.
Pleasure doing business.
- Fire and Rescue.
- Yeah. Hey.
I'm out on Highway 70 by the Pulga Bridge.
Looks like some sort of a grass fire
on the west side of the canyon,
and it's really blowing out here.
Okay. Highway 70 near Pulga Bridge.
Hold on one moment for me, sir.
Okay, I think I see what you're seeing.
Uh, thank you for the report. We will get
the fire department on the way, okay?
He's got…
He's got arms the size of your thighs.
He's-He's like this.
Jarbo Gap. Vegetation fire.
Engine 2161, Engine 2176,
reported vegetation fire
at Highway 70 near the Pulga Bridge.
Please respond.
Oroville, Engine 2161,
Engine 2176 responding.
Up, Simbas!
Let's go, we got work…
Let's go. Let's go. Let's go.
Five more minutes,
I'd have breakfast.
- Good Morning.
- Morning.
Okay. Come on. Clear.
It's gotta be a failed cable.
Right underneath those towers.
You know,
getting to it is gonna be the problem.
What about there?
Can we even get our rigs in there?
It's tight, but let's give it a shot.
All right. Let's back 'em up!
- Let's move.
- Go.
Can't talk right now, Ma.
I'll call you right back.
- Okay. Let's go. Go.
See you later.
- Thank you.
- Bye.
- Uh-huh, see ya.
- Thank you. Have a great day.
- Have a good day.
Watch out on this side.
The road can't take the weight.
Yeah, I see that.
2176, 2161.
Just be careful on the right.
Looks a little shaky.
Copy that, cap.
All right. Heavy smoke ahead.
Don't know about this.
Let's stick with it.
Let's knock this thing out
before it becomes something.
Geez.
Yeah, Ma.
I've been trying
to get a hold of you.
Shaun's throwing up.
He's really not well.
Shit.
Um, does he have a fever?
I don't know. He's in the bathroom.
963, Base calling. Do you read?
Ha-Hang on a second, Ma.
Uh, Base, this is 963.
Have you completed drop-off yet?
Yes, boss. Drop-off complete.
Bring her on in then.
The mechanic's waiting for you.
Okay. Just need to fuel up first.
You're meant to do that
before pickup, 963.
Copy that, boss.
Doing the best I can.
I will be in as soon as I fuel up, okay?
963 out.
Yeah, Ma.
Uh, did you, uh, take his temperature?
I'm looking for the thermometer.
It should be in the first aid kit. Um…
It's not there.
How about under the kitchen sink?
Try there, Ma.
I've gotta pull in to fuel up.
- I'll call you right back, okay?
- Okay.
Come on, come on,
come on, come on, come on.
Come on.
All right, I-I got it. I got it.
- Oroville, Engine 2161.
- Oroville.
I got a visual.
Blowing southwest under the power lines.
Gotta be about 100 acres.
Hey, I don't know about this.
We don't have an escape route.
We're close.
Let's stick with it.
Look at it, cap.
There's no way we're getting up there.
We gotta turn around.
Let's find an alternative strike point.
This route's no good.
Cap, come on.
Okay.
Oroville, Engine 2161.
2161, Oroville. Copy.
We can't reach it down here.
It's too dangerous.
We're gonna head back up the ridge
and see if we can find a new strike point.
Copy that. ICP is being
established at Scooter's on Highway 70.
Resources are out.
Come on.
Let's go!
For Division 2102,
Engine 2186, Engine 2182, Engine 2162,
Transport 2140, Transport 2142.
Butte crew 1, Butte crew 2, Butte crew 3,
vegetation fire reported
in the area of Camp Creek Road.
Respond to staging
at Scooter's on Highway 70.
Yes, keep it coming.
- Okay, what have we got?
- Okay.
Fire started about right here, all right?
We think it's about two to three hundred
acres, so it's sitting about like that.
A really strong east wind
pushed it down canyon.
The Jarbo Gap engines tried to make
access across Camp Creek Road.
They couldn't do it.
Just got too narrow, too steep.
They backed out.
They are now coming up over the ridge,
and they're trying to make access
down from the top.
Have any other engines deployed?
Yeah.  We got five
additional strike teams en route.
Copy that.
Any communities threatened?
Yeah. We got Pulga a mile west.
This is an old gold rush post.
It's uninhabited.
And then we got Concow.
Okay, so this is a good couple miles away.
It's well clear of the fire.
Uh, trailers and cabins mostly.
Eight hundred people.
Retirees, pot smokers,
homesteaders, that kind of thing.
Let's issue
an evac warning just in case.
- Okay.
- What about Paradise?
Chief, it's eight miles
away on the other side of the canyon.
Population's about 27,000.
I don't think it's an issue.
They should be fine.
- Yeah.
- Uh…
- Huh?
- One.
- One what?
- Uh…  …11.
No. No, no, no. Look, it can't be 111.
No, that's impossible.
If it was 111, he'd be dead.
- Pump 1.
- Pump number?
I can't read these numbers.
They're so tiny.
Have Shaun read it for you.
- He's, uh…
- Shaun, are you there?
- …101.
- Shaun, get on the phone, will ya?
So, he-he's got a temperature.
He doesn't want to talk, Kevin.
He-he says he'll speak to you later.
- He probably just needs his mom.
- I'm sure he does need his mom, huh?
- He's sick, but he's here with his dad.
He's got me, and he's got you.
Listen, Ma, I can't talk right now.
I gotta get the bus to the depot.
I'll swing by the drugstore,
get Shaun some medicine.
I'll be home as soon as I can
after work, okay?
Camp IC, Oroville.
We're getting unconfirmed reports
of another fire in that area.
Oroville, Camp IC. Go ahead.
What's its location?
Camp IC, Oroville. We're unsure.
There's a lot of smoke in the area,
and we have a couple cameras down,
but I believe it to be off Rim Road,
north of Concow.
Uh, Oroville, Camp IC copies.
What do you think?
That's a second start or a spot?
We're three miles away.
I don't know how the heck
that would be a spot fire.
That's a long ways
from the-the original fire.
Okay.
- I think we've got two fires.
- Camp IC, we received a call
from PG&E. They advised of a power outage
approximately ten minutes ago
in the Rim Road area of Concow.
- I believe this…
- So it was a power line then.
…is gonna be related to your second start.
There are power lines down in that area.
The PG&E linemen are here.
Do you want them to wait?
- No. I wanna talk to them.
- Okay.
The hell are you guys doing?
I got two fires now.
I need all your lines
in the area shut down,
right away, before I get any more fires.
We had Red Flag Warnings last night.
You guys knew about this.
Why didn't you shut it down then?
Look, we'll get our people down
to the substation to shut it down.
We'll get up to the transmission tower
to secure the downed lines.
I got two fires now.
It's on your headquarters. It wasn't your
fault, but let's get this taken care of.
Messina. Messina.
Send five additional strike teams
to this new start.
Chief, are you
copying this priority traffic?
Camp IC,
Utility 2136. Priority traffic.
Utility 2136, Camp IC. Go ahead.
This is Engineer Hopkins on Utility 2136.
I'm going off duty out in Concow.
We've got a serious situation developing,
be advised.
Heavy smoke
and embers blowing in out here.
- Are you sure about that? In Concow?
- Concow?
That's affirmative.
I'm driving through it now.
Uh, we've got embers
falling around structures.
It's jumped the fucking box.
Correction. We've got a spot fire.
Correction. Multiple spots.
I count one, two, three, big ones.
Rapid rate of spread.
I'm losing visibility fast.
That's a hell of a distance for a spread.
Gotta be at least five miles.
You think it's another set of power lines?
No, no, no. I guarantee
the power's already off up in Concow.
I mean,
that's a lot of distance covered.
Messina.
Listen to me. It's one fire.
- No. No, that--
- It's one fire.
No, that would be impossible
for it to move that way.
- All one damn fire.
- If we got one fire,
you're looking at
a perimeter about… like that.
Okay. Let's send resources to Concow.
Air tankers, engines.
Give him what he needs.
- Tankers. Yeah.
- Copy. You got that?
Okay. So, if we've got fire in Concow,
we have to change
that evac warning to an order.
- Do it.
- Copy.
New containment line is Jordan Hill Road.
All drivers, this is Base.
Listen up.
Uh, well, I guess today's
a real special day
because we just saw
that Cal Fire's got a fire up by Concow.
So, uh, y'all know the drill.
Just stay off the radio,
and be listening for code reds, okay?
963, Base call. You on your way?
Uh, Base, this is 963.
Uh, ETA 15 minutes, boss.
I've got one more quick stop I gotta make.
Kevin, you need
to get bus 963 into the garage,
or you're gonna miss your afternoon route.
I told you,
it's gonna take at least two hours.
Understood, boss. Uh, I've got
a bit of a family situation, okay?
Kevin, I'm not interested, okay?
I need you to get the bus back here now.
The mechanic can't wait around all day.
Copy that, boss.
I'll be there as soon as I can. Over.
- Everyone, evacuate! Let's go!
- Help!
- Go get in that truck, okay?
Everyone, evacuate!
Let's go!
Leave everything.
Leave that. Leave everything.
Get in the car now!
- Hey, is there anyone else inside?
- No.
Anyone inside?
Come on, baby. Let's go.
Fire department!
Guys, let's go.
Leave your bags.
Leave your bags!
- Everyone, evacuate!
- Mommy!
- Leave it.
- We gotta go. Come on!
- No!
I said get her in the car now.
Let's go.
- Do you have a car?
- No.
Go get in that white truck.
Hurry up. Let's go. Hold on tight.
Go!
IC, Utility 2136.
Be advised,
we need medics for multiple burn injuries.
I'm starting a convoy.
We're heading out on Concow Road.
Follow me! Stay close!
Everyone, follow each other!
Everyone, hang on, okay?
- Let's go.
- Hello?
- Do you have any questions
- about--
- Hello?
I'll be with you in a moment.
Okay.
- Uh…
- Sounds good. And they are chewable.
You can eat that.
- That I don't think is a good idea.
Okay.
Ma'am, my son, uh…
He's got a fever, and he's throwing up.
I was on the phone.
- Uh, your son, how old is he?
- Sure.
Fourteen.
- Um, does he have any allergies?
- He's 15, actually.
Yeah. He's 15. No, uh…
- I don't know.
- Food intolerances or anything like that?
I don't think so. No.
Whatever the standard thing is
for-for-for fever and throwing up.
Okay. Sounds like
- Tylenol would be your best bet.
- Yeah.
Great. Thank you.
Great. These are going for $7.25.
- Okay. All right.
- I'll be right there, Linda.
- Would you like a bag?
No. That's good.
You can keep the change.
S-Sir, I can…
- Yeah. Go ahead. Huh? No.
- What's going on, Kevin?
Shaun's been messaging.
Says he wants to come home.
- No.
- He says he wants me to come get him.
- No. That… That's ridiculous.
- Well, he sounds upset.
- What happened?
- Nothing.
We had a little misunderstanding.
I thought he was cutting class.
- Well, was he?
- Was he what?
- Was he cutting class?
- No.
It was my mistake.
He's actually got a stomach flu.
But look, I just picked up some Tylenol,
so everything's fine.
It's not fine, Kevin. Not if he's ill
and saying he wants to come home.
I don't have time
for this right now, Linda.
You hear me? I'm already late to get
the bus to the depot for maintenance.
And you think I got time?
I'm working too, you know?
And Pete and I are supposed
to be going to Colorado tonight.
- Tonight?
- Yes, tonight.
I told you.
My bad. Listen, Linda,
I'm gonna have to call you back.
963 to Base.
Okay, 963. Base call.
You on your way, Kevin?
Are there any updates
on that fire?
Because I'm up here in Magalia,
and I… and I can see the smoke column
o-over the canyon, okay?
- And it's blowing right at us.
- Kevin, there are no updates.
Cal Fire's all over it, okay?
Now, get that bus back here now.
I've already asked you three times.
Now, get back here
or you can look for another job.
Base clear.
Copy that, boss. On my way in.
Camp IC, Camp Air Attack.
Tankers inbound.
ETA four minutes.
Copy. Engines responding.
En route to Concow reservoir,
heading southbound on Jordan Hill Road.
Copy.
Uh, what's the ETA on those engines?
The Paradise engines are 18 minutes out.
Copy that.
Utility 2136, Air Attack is inbound.
18 minutes on those engines.
Negative! That's too long.
We're gonna get burned over here.
Jesus!
- Just hang on, guys.
Camp Air Attack. Air tankers
inbound, retardant drop at the head.
Camp IC, Camp Air Attack.
We're having problems hitting the targets
with these winds.
Air Attack, Camp IC.
I need you to try a second pass.
Chief, the Paradise engines
are 15 minutes out from Concow.
Okay. Oroville, Camp IC.
Camp IC, Oroville. Go ahead.
Uh, Oroville, Camp IC requesting
ten air tankers, six Type 1 helicopters,
one lead plane and 25 additional engines
immediately to Concow.
Camp IC, Oroville copies.
All county aircraft, ten tankers,
six Type 1 copters,
25 additional engines immediately.
Oroville, I copy.
Moving resources to Concow now.
Utility 2136,
can you get onto Camelot Road?
Negative.
The fire's blocked it. I'm cut off.
This thing is going to burn over them.
- Get 'em to the bridge.
- Hoffman Bridge?
- Get 'em to Hoffman Bridge.
- That's the best place.
Utility 2136, can you reach Hoffman Bridge
and shelter in the water?
Camp IC, I'll try.
- All right, listen up!
As soon as I stop the truck,
you're gonna get out,
you're gonna run into the creek!
As soon as you get in the creek,
cover your mouth, protect your airway.
Feet to the fire, okay?
Everyone understand?
- All right, let's go!
- Go! Get in the water now!
Into the water! Let's go!
Hang on! Into the water!
Utility 2136,
multiple residents taking shelter
in the creek!
- Oh, my God!
Goddamn it!
Get as far out as you can!
Come on!
Utility 2136…
burnover imminent!
What's the status on our support?
Utility 2136, copy that.
Air Attack are making their second pass.
Engines are ten minutes out.
Camp IC, Camp Air Attack.
Air tankers inbound now.
Uh, Air Attack, Camp IC copies.
Come on. Come on!
Keep calm!
Camp IC, Engine 2182.
We've got multiple obstacles
in the roadway. We can't get through.
The road is blocked.
Repeating, access is completely blocked.
Air Attack, Camp IC,
give me an update on that drop.
Camp IC, Camp Air Attack.
No impact with the drop. No impact at all.
Damn it, where are those Paradise engines?
I just got word
they're not gonna make it through.
They're stuck. They're not gonna make it.
Stay together! It's coming!
- Stay calm! We'll make it through!
Heads down!
Burnover! Burnover! Burnover!
Utility 2136, what's your status?
Utility 2136, do you copy?
- Answer the radio.
- Come on. Come on.
Utility 2136, do you copy?
It's not good.
Initial wave has passed.
We're sheltering in the creek.
We got multiple burn injuries,
and we need help now!
Utility 2136, copy that.
Hold your position.
We'll get medics in
and dozers inbound to clear an evac path.
You don't understand!
Extreme fire behavior.
Critical rate of spread,
heading west towards Paradise!
- Whoa!
Shaun.
Hey, it's me, Dad. Listen, um…
I'm sorry about last night.
All right.
I'm sorry you're not feeling well.
I just picked up some medicine.
I'll get it to you as soon
as I get home after work. All right?
Listen…
…I need you to do me a favor.
All right, the… fire out in Concow,
I don't think
it's anything to worry about.
But just in case, turn on Channel 7
so you can keep an eye on it.
Okay? I don't…
I don't want Grandma to worry.
You know how she gets worried. Huh?
All right, buddy.
I'll see you after work.
Hope you're feeling better.
Uh, Oroville, Camp IC.
Uh, we gotta get people moving.
Alert Town Hall.
Issue mandatory evacuation warning
for zones 3, 8, 14. East Paradise,
anything east of Pentz Road.
Estimate about 4,000 residents.
Camp IC, Oroville copies.
- Mandatory evacuation zones 3, 8, 14.
- We stay focused.
We have a plan. We stick to it.
Okay.
Yes, I-- I've got it. All right.
They've issued an evacuation order.
Phone lines are down.
Come on.
All right, give me those zones.
- Uh, 3, 8 and 14.
- East Paradise only.
It won't go through. It didn't send.
Okay.
Go!
Camp Air Attack, Camp IC,
I need air support in the canyon now.
We need you to buy us some time.
Chief, look at that fire
coming down towards Paradise.
Camp IC, Camp Air Attack.
We are having zero impact.
The fire is spotting onto
the western side of the canyon.
Wind speed is a real problem.
IC copies. We need outside resources.
Requesting 50 additional
strike teams immediately.
Camp IC, Oroville copies.
That's gonna be extended,
sir, minimum two to three hours.
Chief, if-if we don't get resources
i-into Paradise now,
we're gonna lose this thing.
It's gonna be too late.
We're gonna lose our air support.
It's too dangerous
to fly in these conditions.
There's no way they're gonna continue
in this wind.
Camp IC, Branch 3.
We're being overrun.
The fire is crossing the canyon.
We can't stop it.
Do you copy? We can't stop it.
Okay. Mary's class, sit down.
Class,
we don't all need to look out the window.
It's just another brush fire.
Nothing new. Come sit down.
Take out a book.
- Do we know what we're doing?
- Still no evacuation order.
I'm not waiting.
Okay, let's just get everyone out of here
and home as quickly as we can.
Okay, I'll send an email to parents.
If any of your students have phones
or know their numbers,
- get the parents to collect.
- Okay, but…
but some of my kids
have parents who work out of town,
and the parents will never get here
in time. What do we do about those kids?
Okay.  I'm sure they're gonna
have an alternative collection point.
So, let's just gather together
the students who can't be collected.
And I'll just keep trying Town Hall.
Okay. Thank you.
Okay, um…
Echo. Do you know your mom's phone number?
- Uh-huh.
- You do?
- Great. F--
- 435-232--
Okay. Hold on one second.
I'm gonna ask you to write it down.
Who else knows their mom
or dad's phone number?
- Yeah?
- You said you'd call me back.
I'm sorry. I got distracted.
Look, I don't want to argue.
I'm tired of the same fight every week.
We don't need to argue, Lin.
There's nothing to argue about.
Okay.  I didn't realize
our son was sick.
It was an honest mistake.
You don't need to get involved.
- Then why is he calling me?
I don't know! Linda, he's 15!
He got in a fight with his dad,
and he's calling his mom.
Don't make this a bigger deal than it is.
I'm dealing with it.
Base to 963, what is your location?
- Uh, 963, ETA, ten minutes.
The traffic is backed up over here.
Face it, Kevin.
You're just… unreliable.
No. No,
I'm not doing this right now, Lin.
I'm not gonna sit here and go over
all the ways that I screwed up with you.
Listen, it's been tough…
lately with Dad dying.
Don't use your dad as an excuse.
The funeral was four months ago,
and you barely spoke to him for 20 years.
He ruined your life.
That's what you told me!
That's bullshit, Linda.
That's bullshit. That's a low blow.
I'm sorry.
That wasn't nice.
It's just the first weekend
I've been away with anyone since we…
You know what I mean.
Can you turn the radio down?
I can barely hear you.
Turning it down.
All I'm saying is
I know it's been hard for you,
but you gotta think about Shaun.
He looks at you, and all he sees is…
What?
What does he see when he looks at me?
- Don't make me say it, Kevin.
- No, go ahead, say it. Say it.
- You know what I mean.
- Say it.
There's a reason
why your life is a mess,
and Shaun doesn't want to be with you.
I gotta go.
Base to all drivers.
We're having issues
with the comms over here.
Is everybody hearing me?
Hey, hey, Shaun. Hey, it's Dad.
Listen, uh…
I need to know
you're okay, buddy. I, uh…
Call me back if you're getting
any of these messages, please.
Okay? I gotta, um…
I gotta run…
I gotta run the bus to the depot.
Swinging by maintenance
for a couple of hours, then I'll…
You know what?
I'm coming home right now.
- You hear me, buddy?
I got your medicine on me.
I'll be there in 20 minutes max.
Hey, all drivers, this is Base.
This is an important update.
We are now evacuating East Paradise only.
- What zones?
- East Paradise zones 3, 8 and 14.
That is 3, 8 and 14 only.
Any driver east of Clark
all the way to Pentz,
you need to evacuate
that area immediately.
They're worried about the fire coming
across the canyon from Concow.
So if you have any children on board,
you need to take them west all the way
out of town to the Chico depot.
Repeat, the evacuation muster point
is Chico depot.
Base clear.
Okay, honey. Get in.
- Come on, come on. Stop!
All right, let's, um…
I'll be right back.
All right, so we got the evac order.
Apparently, their system went down,
and they weren't able to get it out.
They want every student
who hasn't already been collected
to be taken over to Paradise Elementary.
Okay? That's the new collection point.
That's where they're sending
all the parents.
Okay. Well,
we have 23 kids without transport.
So how are we gonna get them there?
I can take four in my car.
- I didn't drive, so I can't help at all.
- No, no.
We cannot
get them there by ourselves.
We don't have enough cars.
- Yes.
- They need to send us a bus.
- Call Ruby.
- Oh, yeah. I'll call the depot.
Hi, Anna. It's, um… It's Mary.
Look, they're evacuating East Paradise,
and I can't get to Jake.
Steven's out of town for work.
And I was wondering
if you could go get him,
and then I'll just get
to you as soon as I can.
Um, okay. Thank you.
Uh, let me know that you got this.
All right? Love you. Bye.
Unified Schools
Transportation Office.
Uh, I'm sorry.
Uh, can you… Can you speak up please?
It's the principal of Ponderosa.
Yes, ma'am.
Yes, ma'am. Yes, ma'am.
They need a bus to take them west
to the alternative collection
point at Paradise Elementary.
Just outside the evac zone.
Do we have anybody on a route over there?
Check the route maps.
- Cesar.
- Yeah?
I need you to go out
and prep a bus just in case.
- All right.
- Yes, ma'am.
We are gonna get a bus
right out to you, okay?
So you just sit tight. Okay?
Thank you so much.
All right. Bye-bye.
Uh, Base to all drivers,
this is an update on that evac notice.
We have a situation.
Ponderosa Elementary.
I repeat, there's a situation developing
at Ponderosa Elementary.
There are 23 kids who are stranded
in the evacuation zone.
Their parents cannot make it
in to pick them up.
They need to be picked up
and taken to the alternative
collection point at Paradise Elementary.
Is there anybody empty
and in the area of East Paradise?
987 to Base.
Sorry, all full.
Not reached my school yet.
910 to Base.
Full here too, Ruby.
Ten minutes from dropping off.
Come on.
922 to Base,
I'm en route to Chico.
I'm just passing Base,
but I can swing back.
No, 922. Do not swing back.
Once you get out of there, you get out.
Those roads are gonna get
real crazy real quick, okay?
Is there anybody in East Paradise
with an empty bus
that can go and pick these kids up?
No. No.
963 to Base, I can get 'em.
Kevin, is that you?
Yeah.
Yeah, I'm still on this side of town.
Remember?
I was running late.
Yep, yep. I remember.
So, uh, we can do maintenance
another day, okay?
Listen, if you get those kids out,
you will have done well.
Okay, Kevin? You copy?
Copy that. Have them lined up.
I'm on my way.
- "And it was…"
Oh, there's the bus.
Okay, okay, okay. Stay seated.
Stay sitting please, everybody.
Twenty kids for evac?
They're in there. Around to the right.
- Hi.
- Are you here for the kids?
- Yes, I am. Are they… Are they ready?
Um, yep.
We're gathering them up right now.
- Okay.
- Um, what's your name?
- Kevin. And, uh…
- Kevin, hi. I'm Mary.
- Hi. As soon as we can gather…
- Yeah, great. We are…
- We're gonna get 'em in line in a minute.
- Yeah.
These kids, their parents
couldn't make it 'cause they work too--
- Paradise Elementary. Got it.
- Right. The alternative drop-off.
Yep. Got it. Ready to go.
- Principal Hayes. Thank you for coming.
- Hi. Yep.
- Okay…
- Sooner the better.
…and we're just gonna keep it calm
for the kids.
Kids, this is our bus driver, Kevin.
Can we say hi to Kevin?
Hi, Kevin.
Can I get you
in two straight lines?
Shortest in the front.
Tallest in the back.
And Kevin is gonna drive you
to Paradise Elementary,
where your parents
are going to pick you up.
I'm gonna lead the line, Principal.
If you could please take the back
and do a head count while we walk.
If you're ready, raise your hand.
Let me see your eyes. Eyes on me.
I want to see everybody's eyes.
- Are we ready?
- Yes.
We're gonna walk calmly.
We're gonna walk slowly.
We're gonna stay with our partners.
- Okay, here we go.
- Yeah. Come on.
- What do you think, like, ten minutes?
- Uh, yeah, if we get a move on, yes.
But the traffic's getting really busy
out there. So the quicker, the better.
Okay. We have time.
Well, you know, ma'am,
I don't think you understand
the urgency of our situation here.
I recognize the urgency of our situation.
And it's Mary, not "ma'am."
Hoods up if you have a hood!
If you have a backpack, put it on top.
- Okay! It's okay! It's okay! It's okay!
It's just a fire engine in the sky!
Use your backpacks, okay?
All right.
Find a seat on the bus, babe.
Quietly, calmly, one single line.
Not quickly, take your time.
963 to Base,
we're loading the kids on the bus now.
The signal's bad.
I'll let you know when we're clear, over.
Everybody, I want you to stay seated
and listen to everything Kevin says.
- Okay?
- W-Wait, wait, wait!
Alex! I need Alex!
- Alex? Alex, honey, your mom is here.
- Alex!
Okay, you have all your things?
- You gotta go. Okay.
- Oh, thank God.
Let's go. Let's go. Let's go.
Okay, you are good to go.
Whoa, whoa, whoa.
Ma'am, ma'am. Whoa, whoa, whoa.
No, no. Y-You're coming. Yes.
No. No.  I have to lock up.
No, no, no, no. Y-You can't. I…
I'm gonna drive and drop. Okay?
I can't hang about
and hold any hands when I get there.
I've got my own family
I gotta get home to.
Okay? You gotta come.
I-I don't think he can do this by himself.
I have to go with him.
- Pipe down!
- It's fine.
I'll get a ride
from one of the teachers there.
- Here, take the evac for HQ.
- You okay to lock up alone?
- Yeah.
- All right. I'm here. I'm here.
- I'm coming.
- We're good.
- Hang on.
We got on the bus.
We're gonna be there.
It's gonna take ten minutes.
Did you see those fire engines?
Okay, um, here is the school's evac route.
We are… the East line, so we're gonna
stay on Pentz all the way down,
and then cut a right on Pearson
to get us to Paradise Elementary.
I don't-I don't think
it's a good idea. L-Look at it.
T-There's
a better way out than Pentz right.
Okay, but that's the plan.
So we're gonna stick to the plan.
Whatever you say, teach.
It's total gridlock.
Look how tight those roads are right now.
It's gotta be at least 15 miles
of traffic trying to get to Chico.
Chief,
we're arriving at the fairgrounds.
Copy that.
I'm issuing a mandatory evacuation
on the whole town.
All zones. Effective immediately.
Chief, you can't do it. It'll be chaos.
We're talking 26,000 people.
If you get everyone moving out of town,
you're never gonna get your engines in.
You're not listening.
The fire's coming across the canyon.
I've seen it with my own eyes.
It's moving fast.
Here's the choice,
bust the system or play by the book
and everybody dies.
You want that on your conscience?
Chief, we got the team
ordered early for ya.
- Copy.
- All right.
Hey, Chief. Chief. Mark Rogers of PG&E.
I have a team here from headquarters.
We're available.
Just get the power off in the town,
and we'll take care of the rest.
- Yeah.
- Okay, listen.
We gotta give the chief some space.
We will come to you in a second.
Just… No, just wanted to say
we're available if you need us.
Issue mandatory evac
order for the entire town.
Copy, Chief.
Oroville, Camp Ops.
Base to 179, 179. Are you clear?
Are you out of East Paradise?
- 179. We're out.
- Great, great.
Who's left?
963 is the only one left.
That's all.
Base to 963.
Base to 963, are you out of East Paradise?
963 to Base.
Do you read?
Don't be scared. The-The
fire trucks are responding to the fire.
- They're doing their job.
- Anybody, 963 to Base.
- They're keeping us safe.
- Can anybody hear me?
Okay? We are on Pentz.
It is backed up going nowhere.
963, come in please.
Can you try his mobile?
Why does he have to be the last bus
out of there? I swear to God.
963 to Base, do you read?
Let me know if you're getting this. Over.
Do you have any safety protocols
on this bus?
Yep. You got this,
and you got that.
Great. Yeah.
That'll make all the difference.
So you're new here?
No, I just came back a few months ago.
Grew up here.
Oh. What's that like?
Not where I thought I'd be at 44.
How long do you think this is gonna take?
Hard to tell.
If we'd have left the school on time,
you wouldn't have slow played me,
it would have taken about ten minutes,
but now it's looking like 20-30.
Guess we'll get there when we get there.
Okay, kiddies.
Let's, um, raise some of these windows
so the smoke doesn't get in.
- Hi. Is this fire command?
This is Ruby Bishop at PUSD.
I've lost all radio communication,
and I have a lost bus.
It's number 963,
and it's over somewhere in East Paradise.
Can you let me know
if your engines see him?
Thank you.
Okay, okay. Okay, uh…
963, do you read?
Kevin? Can you… Can you hear me?
This is Base.
Honey, let's, um…
move this up so smoke doesn't get in.
- What's your name?
- Benjamin.
Benjamin, and you're in Miss Kristy's
class? That's right. I remember that.
Miss Mary,
there's another window.
Yes. Let's get that one.
Screw this.
- Kevin!
What are you doing?
The plan is to stay on Pentz!
Turning over to Clark. It runs parallel.
It's bound to be moving better.
But that's not the plan.
- The plan is to stay on Pentz.
- Screw the plan, teach.
You know what?
Hey, I could stay here
in the middle of the traffic jam
if that's what you want.
- Don't stop now, obviously.
- Want me to stay here?
No shit. Let me drive.
- What the hell is your problem?
- Look, you see that fire?
It's like the fucking
Fourth of July, okay?
I'd sit down if I were you.
I'm about to take a hard left.
- Bunch down, everybody!
- Hold on!
Oh, my God! Oh, my God! Hold on, kids!
- Oh, my God! Kevin!
- Hold on!
- Jesus. Jesus Christ.
- We're clear.
- Is everyone okay?
We're okay. Traffic is moving.
Can you please ask before
you do something like that again?
You wanna get there quicker
or you wanna go by the book?
We have to be responsible.
Yep, and I think that means getting these
kids to their parents as soon as possible.
Don't you?
- I'm not getting anything.
- Kevin, come in please.
This is a code red
alert. Evacuate all zones immediately.
Ruby, we gotta go.
I gotta get the power off.
- I know.
- I'm getting my guys outta here.
Okay, okay. Uh, take my keys. Okay?
963, do you read?
So, what about you? You always lived here?
Yeah. Born and raised.
Never was really my speed.
Then why'd you come back?
My dad died a few months ago.
- Sorry.
- Nah, it's fine.
We weren't close.
So you staying?
- For now.
What about you? Got family?
Yeah.
Married 19 years.
A Paradise poster family too, huh?
Yeah.
- One kid.
- Hmm.
Jake. He's 15.
I was gonna go get him, but…
I didn't realize. Sorry.
It's fine.
My sister will have gone for him.
His dad's out of town.
It'll be fine.
We're gonna drop the kids off,
and then I'll go find him.
- All right. How're we doing?
- Are we gonna be okay?
Yes. We're gonna be okay, sweetie.
Are our pets okay?
When will we see our parents?
We'll see them there, yeah?
We're just trying to get you
to safety as soon as we can, okay?
- Yes, sweetie?
When are we going to be there?
We're gonna be there
as soon as we can, okay?
You okay, sweetie?
Mm-hmm.
Do you want to sit up front
with somebody else,
or do you want to be by yourself?
Kevin, if you can hear me,
they're evacuating the whole town,
and emergency services
are mustering 15 miles away
- at Chico Fairgrounds where it's safe.
Do not drop those kids off.
Just take 'em and come to Chico. Okay?
Ruby, we're outta time.
We gotta go.
- I gotta get my guys out of here.
- Okay!
Ruby!
Kevin, if you can hear me,
I will see you in Chico, okay?
Be careful. Base clear.
Come on!
Chief, the fire's spreading
fast through East Paradise.
And I just got word from Division Hotel.
You got a working fire in the cardiology
wing at Feather River Hospital.
It's well established in the attic.
You got about 15 to 20 patients
that are outside right now.
We're working on getting them outta there.
Do whatever you can in there
and save the hospital, okay?
Get me Butte medics,
and tell them we need help.
Chief.
Air Attack has grounded all aircraft.
Now, I'll get you
an update as soon as I can,
but right now nothing goes in the air.
- Nothing.
- Goddamn it.
Where are we with the evacuation route?
How's this traffic moving?
You can see now
the fires across from Clark Road,
they're getting impacted by fire.
Pentz Road is gridlocked.
Skyway is still open. It's moving slow.
But what about all these abandoned cars?
We're having major access issues.
I want any vehicle blocking
traffic pushed off the road.
Okay? Get dozers in there if you have to.
Got it.
We can't lose
those four routes out.
We lose those, it's game over.
- Hey, everybody! Listen up! Listen up!
- Everybody, quiet!
This is no longer a wildland fire.
This is burning home to home.
This is a town fire.
This is a mass casualty incident.
That's what we're dealing with.
So stay on with your people,
and do the best you can.
- Copy, Chief.
- Copy that.
Hey! What's the holdup?
Got a roadblock up ahead!
The freeway's jammed.
Shit!
Come on.
Where do you need to get to?
- After we drop off the kids.
- Magalia.
My son's up there with his grandma.
I told them I'd be coming straight home.
Well, they'll get the evacuation alerts.
Won't they?
You signed up for them, right?
I…
You know, I-I kept getting the noti…
…notifications from the town hall
and I just kept putting it off.
Well, can his grandma drive?
Nope.
Miss Mary, help.
Miss Mary,
there's smoke coming from that house.
Fire on the left.
- Fire on the left. Bunch down.
- Stay away from the windows.
Everybody stay off the windows.
Hey.
Just let me in!
Come on!
Buddy, I got kids on the bus.
Stay calm.
Kevin's trying to get us through.
Mary, take a seat.
- What? Why?
- Take a seat. I need you to drive.
- I need you to drive.
- I don't know how.
I've gotta clear traffic in the left lane.
I need you to take over the bus.
It's easy. Okay?
You put your foot on the brake,
when I say come, hit the gas.
It's easy. Okay? Yes, you do.
Hold the brake.
- Okay.
- When I say, "Come on," come on.
- Okay?
- Okay.
Stay seated.
Where's Kevin?
Back it up.
Back this truck up.
We gotta get this fire engine in.
- Let's go. Keep 'em going!
- Hey, hey, hey. What's going on?
- What're you doing? What's the plan?
- We got people trapped on Pentz.
Those people got priority.
- The main fire's over there.
- See the school bus?
I have 22 kids on that bus.
I gotta get them to their parents, okay?
Where's Kevin?
I need you to hold traffic here
so we can come through.
I gotta clear this traffic
to let the fire truck through.
Get on the radio
and call fuckin' backup, will you?
Our comms are down. They've been
down for about 40 minutes or so.
Get back in your car.
We'll get you through when we can.
Get back in your car, sir.
- Get back in your car.
- Go left.
We gotta get the fire truck
and this bus through first.
Go! Go!
Go, go, go! Go, go, go!
Hold it!
- Go!
Come on.
Okay.
Let the fire truck and the bus through!
Come on, go, go, go, go!
Yes.
Go! Go!
Come on. Come on!
I-I don't want to hit you.
Are we gonna be okay?
Come on.
Come on!
Holy shit.
Yes!
We did it. We made it through.
What was wrong?
Radios are down. It's chaos.
A minute out, minute out.
Minute out! Are we ready?
963. We are one minute out from drop-off.
One minute out from drop-off.
Nice driving.
Thanks. Not so bad yourself.
You could always be a traffic cop
if you're looking for a fresh start.
I'd take a hard pass on that.
Okay, kids. You can get your things ready.
Be ready to get off the bus.
I'm gonna get you to your parents
as quickly as we can.
- Our parents…
- The school's…
- Oh, my God.
- No! Where are they?
- No, no, no, no, no. No, no.
- Where are they?
Oh, shit!
I want my mom.
I'll go see if anybody's there.
Hello!
They're… They're not here.
There's no one here.
I don't know why they didn't warn us or…
What do we do?
I don't know.
What…
We gotta get outta here.
We gotta get these kids out of here.
Try to get them down
to the main evac center in Chico.
And then we can come back for our kids.
Miss Mary!
I'm coming. I'm coming.
Sit down.
- Ava needs you.
- What's wrong with Ava?
She won't come
from under her seat.
- What? She's on the floor?
- Yeah, she needs you.
- Why? What's wrong with her?
- She won't get up!
- She's scared.
- Ava. Honey, no.
What are you doing down there?
- Are you okay?
No?
- It's all a little bit scary.
- Okay.
- Mary, are we good?
- Yeah. Good to go.
Okay.
Are you scared?
- Yeah.
I know.
I'm scared too.
Can I give you a hug?
Mm-hmm.
There you go. Come on.
Be as brave as you can be.
Chief, you've got 27,000 people
in Paradise,
12,000 in Magalia.
You've got maybe 8,000 people evacuated,
which means you've got 30,000 people
left in the footprint of the fire.
Finney, come here a second.
Update on the infrastructure.
How we doing with that?
So, infrastructure, Chief,
we got multiple schools in the town here.
We have two that are being impacted
immediately along-along Pentz road.
I also have a report that a school bus
came out of Ponderosa Elementary
with 22 kids on it.
It's unaccounted for right now, but--
Keep me updated on that.
We also have multiple gas stations.
We have two propane facilities.
One in Skyway in between Pentz and Clark
and another one in Magalia.
- Can you shut them down?
- I'll work on it.
Part of the evacuation
problem, power lines are coming down.
They cannot get across the road.
Firefighters are cutting them right now
to open it up, but we're getting reports--
Where's PG&E?
We're getting reports
of active power lines.
- PG&E.
- Yeah.
- I thought the power was off.
- It is.
Tell them what's going on.
Why is your power on?
It's… Look, we're working on it.
We got civilians
driving across power lines.
- We got firefighters cutting lines…
- I understand.
- …and lines are still arcing?
- You told me the power was off.
- Look. All the automatic power is off.
Thereafter it's manual switches
that have to be done.
- We're working as fast as we can.
- I don't give a shit.
- I understand.
- Do you know what's going on here?
Shut the fucking power off!
- Okay.
- What the fuck is wrong with you?
I've got firefighters in there!
There's 30,000 people in there!
What the hell are we gonna do?
The fire's behind us.
We gotta stay ahead of it
and stay due southwest.
That clear patch of sky,
that's our way out.
We stay out of the fire,
and we head down to Chico from there.
Um, Pentz and-and Clark are out,
- so that leaves Neal and Skyway.
- Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
Neal is the furthest away,
but maybe that's good.
Maybe there's less traffic there.
But you have to take Roe Road
to get to Neal.
It's-It's narrow,
and it's full of 180 degree turns.
It's-it's not built
for a 35,000 pound bus.
We'd be trapped down there.
There's no way out.
- That really just leaves us Skyway.
- Skyway. Right.
- It's-It's wide, four lanes, straight.
- Yeah.
- Let's try Skyway. Okay.
- Skyway.
You don't know where they are, do you?
What, honey?
Our parents.
You don't know where they are.
No, honey, we don't,
but we're gonna find them.
We're gonna find their parents,
right, Kevin?
Yeah. Yeah, we're gonna find them. Yeah.
I need you to take your seat, sweetie.
You wanna sit down up here?
- Have a seat.
- Here.
Yeah, this is fine.
What's your name?
Toby.
Your parents work out of town?
My mom does.
I don't see my dad.
I'll tell you what, Toby.
We're gonna get you back to your mom.
You hear me?
We're gonna get you back to your son,
and we're gonna get me back to mine.
That's what's going to happen.
Okay?
Okay.
So, Chief, the fire is
spreading through most of Paradise,
both business and residential areas,
and we're getting reports
of significant structure loss,
and Air Attack is still grounded
with no ETA.
- Copy that.
- Hey, Chief.
I've-I've checked in with division.
Last report of that bus was coming down
Clark Road south of Elliott. Okay?
I just got word from Division Hotel
that Paradise Elementary
is well involved in fire.
They're not there.
Mary, can you see these cables?
- Yeah.
- All right.
- Oh, my God. Watch out.
Got it. Got it. Got it.
- Kevin, on the right! Kevin!
Power line on the right!
- The whole road's coming down.
- Oh, my God.
It's falling! It's falling!
Watch out! Watch out!
- Oh, my God.
Going left!
It's gonna cut through to Skyway.
We can make it. It's just down here.
Kids, hold on! Hold onto something!
- Hang on!
- Oh, my God.
Shit!
Keep it in check!
Back it up! Come on back!
We're blocked.
We're totally blocked in.
We gotta get off, find a way to Roe,
and try to make a way out on Neal.
It's our only chance right now.
- How are we gonna get out of here?
- Look for a way off. Left or right.
I'm looking. I'm looking.
I don't see anything. There's no way out.
I don't see… It's everywhere.
It's all around us.
How are we gonna get out of here?
Oh, my God!
Look straight ahead.
- Don't look at that.
- Straight ahead!
Get out the fucking car!
Kevin, there's looters.
- Open up. Let me in!
- Get off the windows!
Stay away from the windows!
- Down! Get down!
- Stay away from the windows!
Give us the bus!
- Mary!
- Open it!
He has a gun! Kevin, he has a gun!
Open it!
- Down! Duck. I said duck.
Open the door!
- We have to get out of here.
We have to get out of here.
On the left.
On the left, Kevin, there's a gap.
Kevin, there's a gap. Go left.
Left. Go, go, go, go.
It's closing. It's closing.
We're through. We're through.
Stay with your family, please.
This is the safe area, sir.
We need you to stay here…
- Let's go. Let's go.
- That's my daughter.
- Out of the way.
- Watch your back.
- Go!
- Move!
Just keep going.
Just keep going. Just keep going.
Whoa, whoa. Hold on.
I'm with the, uh,
Paradise Unified School District.
- Where are you from?
- Straight up.
Thank you.
That's where the busses are.
Okay. Thank you. Just keep going.
This is the… Yeah, there they are.
There they are.
Let me out. Let me out. Let me out.
- Cesar?
- Ruby.
Cesar. You heard any news?
- Nothing.
- 963's not here?
Hasn't made it back yet.
Shit.
Ruby, the parents are here.
Okay. Okay. Okay.
963 to Base. 963 to Base.
Do you read?
- Miss Mary, I don't have any water left.
- 963 to all vehicles.
- Do you read? Any vehicles, do you read?
- I'm thirsty. I'm way too hot.
Okay. Okay.
Here, honey.
Get a folder or a… a notebook
or something…
Hey, listen, we just got off Skyway.
It was a no-go.
Here. Use it like this.
We're gonna try
and-and-and make our way out through Neal.
Stay out of the fire.
Get out that way. It's our only shot.
Miss Mary, we really need some water.
Hang in there, sweetie.
I know. It's really hot.
Kevin, the kids are not gonna last.
They need water.
They're hot, and they're thirsty.
- What's happening?
- What is that?
What the hell is that?
I can't breathe.
It's coming through the vents.
The smoke. The smoke is getting in.
Kevin, the smoke is coming in.
It's coming through the AC.
Then turn it off.
It's gonna make the heat worse, but okay.
We have to try something.
Okay, it's off. Off.
We must be inside the smoke column.
- Watch out.
- Yeah. Yeah. I see it. I see it.
Meadow Creek Park.
Yeah. Yeah. There's… There's a back exit.
What?
I worked here one summer as a kid.
It leads out to Roe Road,
and then we can get over to Neal,
and then we're out. Okay?
- Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
- Yes.
Miss. Ma'am.
- Yeah?
- There's something wrong with Shannon.
- She needs your help.
- She's wheezing a little bit.
- What's wrong, honey?
- Okay. Okay. Don't talk. Don't talk.
Just breathe slowly, okay? Slowly.
Try to slow down your breathing.
Okay. You just need to drink some water.
Um, can everybody
just look in their backpack
and make sure you don't have,
like, a juice box or something?
Kevin, we… we have to find water
or she's gonna stroke out.
We have to get off the bus now.
- Right there. Right there.
- Yep, yep.
- Yes. Yes. Okay.
Okay. We can't stop for long.
I'll be two minutes.
No, no, no, no, no, no.
You need to stay on the bus.
If the fire comes, you have to drive them.
Let me go. I can do it.
Two minutes. I'll be right back.
I can do it.
Miss Mary, where are you going?
Miss Mary.
Miss Mary, come back.
- Where did Mary go?
Shit.
Do you know
where Miss Mary is?
She…
She just went to look for some water.
Just-Just give her a minute.
Please come back, Miss Mary.
Where is she going?
I can't see her.
Come on.
Come back.
Yes. Yes.
Got it.
Oh, my God. Got it.
Mary!
- Mary!
- What do we do now?
- I'm coming!
I'm coming!
- Go, go, go, go.
- Help me. Help me.
Get the water. Get the water.
Miss Mary's here.
- Okay.
- You okay?
I'm okay. I'm okay. I'm okay.
Can somebody get this water to Shannon?
- Oh, my God!
Duck! Down! Cover your heads!
- Shit!
- Oh, my God!
Everybody, hold on!
Stay away from the windows.
Everyone, hold on!
Oh, my God.
We gotta go right. That's the way out.
- Oh, my God!
Hold on!
Okay. Stay down. Stay down.
On the right. On the right. On the right.
- That burnt building on the right.
This is the way out.  That's it.
Here it is. This is the exit.
This takes us to Roe.
Hello, everyone.
If I could get y'all in.
Uh, my name is Ruby Bishop.
I am the school's
director of transportation,
and I just wanna give you an update.
I know y'all are worried,
but I want you to know first and foremost
that your children were evacuated
from Ponderosa Elementary
earlier this morning. Okay?
When will we know more?
Unfortunately,
shortly after leaving the school,
the fire destroyed
our radio communication.
So we have not had contact
with the bus since it left Ponderosa.
Wait, you don't know where they are?
All I know is that they're probably
somewhere over in East Paradise.
East Paradise is on fire!
I know, but I want you to know
that both police and fire command
are looking for them out there, okay?
They're doing their best,
but you must know that your children
are on the bus
with a driver
and a teacher named Mary Ludwig.
- Some of you may know Mrs. Ludwig?
- Okay.
- Which… Which driver is it?
Yes. His-His name is Kevin McKay.
He's a new driver to our district.
- New driver?
- Listen…
- Everybody, please.
Please. I know.
I know this is really difficult news.
- He's a good driver.
- Kevin McKay.
I can vouch for Kevin McKay,
as can all of my drivers.
He is a good man,
and he is gonna do everything he can.
You have to trust him.
I trust him, and right now
he is all we have got out there. Okay?
This is it.
This is Roe Road.
Fire's behind us.
Okay, a couple of miles on this
should get us out towards Neal.
Okay.
Rocks on the right. Rocks on the right.
Watch your left.
- There's a drop-off.
- I'm scared.
We're gonna be okay, guys.
You don't need to worry.
We're gonna get through this, okay?
Watch out.
Mary.
What do I have over there?
Four feet?
Two.  Maybe two and a half.
Chief,
our fire in Butte Creek Canyon
and our fire in the west branch
have merged in Paradise.
It's burning aligned with the wind,
burning to the southwest portion
of Paradise.
The only area that hasn't burned,
and the fire is heading in this direction,
is this area right here.
Foster Road. Roe Road.
Hey, these are tight roads.
A lot of structures in there.
It's all downhill.
You've got numerous spot fires
being reported down here already.
This area's gonna be fully engulfed
in fire very soon.
We have got zero resources
to put down here.
They're all engaged up here.
Whatever's down here,
they're gonna have to figure out for
themselves how to get out of Paradise.
We've got nothing to give 'em.
Absolutely nothing.
Miss Mary.
What are they doing over there?
Who are those people?
- What are they doing?
Why are they going back towards the fire?
Here! Here!
- Yo! Hey! Hey! Stop! Stop!
No, no, no, no.
Come around this side.
Is there a way out down there?
That fire's burning
across the ridge.
- People are dying down there.
- We got out on foot.
Do not go that way.
The trailer park, everything is burning.
Everything. There's no way out.
- What the hell are we gonna do?
- I-I just need to get to Neal Road.
No, you can't go to Neal Road.
It's on fire.
You don't want these kids
to see what we just saw.
Trust me.
Do not go that way.
Hey, we're gonna take our chances.
Shit.
Good luck.
What do we do?
Why have we stopped?
- No, keep going.
- I wanna go home.
Okay. Everyone, we just need
to stay quiet and calm, please.
And Kevin and I,
we'll, uh, figure this out.
We need to keep moving.
Okay. I'm gonna go have a look.
Check this ridge and this ridge.
Get the kids ready in case
we have to take them off the bus, okay?
Okay.
Kevin, what are you doing?
Don't go.
- Okay. Okay.
Okay. Kids, this is what
I need for us to do.
I need us to stay quiet.
I need us to stay calm.
Kevin is going to check
if it's okay for us to get off the bus.
- In the meantime…
…I want you to grab your backpack
and make a line in the aisle.
Slowly, quietly,
as calmly as you can, please.
Come on.
Okay. As soon as Kevin gets back,
we're gonna file off, okay?
Yes, ma'am.
We're gonna stay really close.
You're gonna find someone's hand
to hold, okay?
Stay really, really close.
- Look. Kevin, he's back.
There he is.
Get the kids. Seat the kids.
- We're staying on the bus.
- Okay.
- Staying on the bus.
- Okay. Everybody, sit down.
- Wait. Wait. What?
- Everybody, sit.
Miss Mary,
I thought you said we were gonna go.
I did, honey. But…
…we're gonna stay on the bus.
Uh, Henry, you're…
Take a seat. We're gonna…
Kevin and I are gonna figure out what…
- What happened?
- We're surrounded.
- Oh, my God.
- There's nowhere to go.
What? No. No, no, no.
That's impossible. It's impossible.
- There's gotta be a way out.
- Listen to me.
- We're here on Roe.
- Okay. Okay.
- This is Neal.
- Okay.
I saw it all from the ridge, okay?
The fire's on all sides.
It's here, it's here, here and here.
- Oh, my God.
- We gotta st… We gotta stay here.
We gotta… We gotta stay on the bus.
We're gonna stay on the bus.
No.
- No. We…
- We're gonna stay on the bus.
No. We… No. No. No.
We could go out on foot.
Those other people, they went out on foot.
- We could try on foot.
- No. No way.
They won't last two minutes out there.
There's no way.
They won't last…
They won't last two minutes.
Gotta stay.
What? What, we stay here?
We just…
What do you…
We're just gonna wait? What do…
- Maybe… Maybe the fire doesn't…
- What if the fire comes, but we--
Maybe it does
or maybe it doesn't come, okay?
I d… I don't know.
All I do know is we are in
the one place where the fire is not.
And we're alive right now.
And we got a little bit of time.
Stay.
That's our only chance.
Are you sure?
Yes.
But what if the fire comes?
What if the fire comes, Kevin?
Listen to me.
What do we do with the kids
if the fire comes?
We gotta stay on the bus.
Okay.
- Okay?
- Okay.
Okay.
We'll stay on the… We'll stay on the bus.
We'll stay on the bus.
Mary, hey. I need your help.
We gotta buy some time.
I'm gonna cut my shirt up
into small pieces. All right?
What are you doing?
I'm gonna make some filters
for their mouths.
Wet them with some water.
It can soothe their throats.
Let's move the kids to the back of the bus
away from the… the air vents.
I'm gonna tape as many vents
as I can, okay?
Okay.
Chief, the water supply is failing.
We've got no pressure in the hydrants.
We are losing this thing.
Can I talk to you over here for a second?
So we're gonna rest
for a little bit,
and I wanna move you
to the back of the bus
so that you're further away
from the smoke, okay?
Okay, Miss Mary.
Honey, can we move
to the back of the bus, all right?
Come on, this way.
That should help to keep
some of the smoke out, okay?
So we're getting reports
of people burning to death in their cars.
And we've got hundreds of people
running for their lives on foot.
Okay, girls.
We're gonna be here for a little while.
I want you to take this filter,
put it over your mouth
and your nose and breathe, okay?
If we don't play this right,
we're gonna wake up in the morning
to hundreds or, I don't know,
even thousands of fatalities.
Okay? So at this point,
we can do one thing.
We can fight fire or save lives.
We are out of time.
I want you to put it over your mouth
and your nose and breathe.
- It's gonna help with the smoke, okay?
- Okay.
- Yeah? How are you doing, sweetie?
- How long are we staying here?
Thank you for
taking care of her, sweetie.
Mmm.
Ava, I want you
to put this over your mouth.
Okay, listen up.
Cease all firefighting.
Get with your resources inside town
and tell them to save lives
wherever they can.
That's all we can do now.
Copy that, Chief.
Hurry up.
The windows are so hot.
- I have to warn the kids.
- No, no, no. I can do it.
- No, no. I can… I'm good. I can do it.
- I… I know… I know you can.
Rest for a second. I… I can do it.
Okay. Thank you.
Hey, guys.
The walls and the windows
are really hot, so… so don't touch them.
Okay? I want you to come…
lean towards the aisle.
Here we go.
Can you come this way a little bit?
The floor's really hot too.
Let's do the, um…
What do you do at story time?
Let's go crisscross? Apple sauce?
Say it with me.
- Crisscross apple sauce.
- Crisscross.
That's it, that's it. That's it.
Good. Good job, buddy. Okay.
Is it nighttime?
What's that, sweetie?
No, no, no. It's not nighttime.
It's just… It's smoke.
It's in between us and the sunshine. Okay?
Are we gonna be okay?
Yeah.
We are gonna be… Yes, we are.
And that smoke's gonna go away,
and the sun's gonna come back out.
Okay?
Toby, you okay?
I want my daddy.
Yeah.
Yeah, I know you do.
He knows you do too. Okay?
Listen.
He's… He's doing everything
he can to get to you.
Okay? And he's trying his best.
- Okay? Toby, look at me.
Okay?
How much time do we have?
Another hour maybe.
Those filters won't last much longer.
Maybe we should just let them go to sleep.
It's better.
Then if the fire comes…
- No, no, no. No. No. No.
We can't… We can't let ourselves
talk like that. Okay?
Okay.
Good afternoon.
I'm Chief Martinez.
At approximately 6:30 a.m. this morning,
a fire was reported near the Pulga Bridge,
eight miles east of Paradise.
The fire spread rapidly,
overwhelming our best efforts
to contain it.
And at approximately 8:30 a.m.
this morning,
the fire entered the town of Paradise.
Unfortunately, moments ago,
I was forced to give the order
to cease firefighting in Paradise
and focus solely on protecting life.
Right now, there's still thousands
of residents trapped
or attempting to flee the fire.
And while we are doing everything
we humanly can to assist them…
despite our best efforts,
this community is facing
the full force of the fire alone.
So we ask for your patience,
and I'll hand it over to Sheriff Thomas,
who may have more information for you.
We have to get back to work. Thank you.
I just wanna add one thing.
Every year the fires get bigger.
And there's more of them.
We're being damn fools.
That's the truth. Thank you.
This is gonna sound silly to you…
but I've only ever left Paradise one time.
Oh.
How's that?
To go to Ohio.
Two weeks.
On my friend's farm.
And one time, Steven and I
did a weekend in San Francisco.
I thought that I'd be safe here.
Just stay in Paradise.
Stay with him. Follow the rules.
And nothing bad could truly happen.
But that's no way to live a life.
Hiding away.
That's one thing I'd change
if we get out of here.
I'd take a trip.
I'd take Jake to Legoland.
Or Africa maybe. I don't know.
I would love to see elephants.
Animals at a watering hole.
Anything really. Just anything.
Before it's too late.
Why are you laughing?
Ah.
I've spent my entire life
trying to escape Paradise,
and now for some reason
all I wanna do is make a go of it here.
Why did you wanna leave?
You know, when I first got
the call to go pick up the kids,
uh, I started to think that maybe…
maybe I could earn a second chance
if I just got the kids out safe,
you know?
Except they don't always
work that way. Second chances.
Why do you say that?
The last time I spoke to my dad
was 28 years ago.
I was 16. It was Christmas Eve. And, uh…
We got into a fight.
Something about me
not finishing what I started.
Same kind of shit,
same fight it always was.
Anyway, he, uh…
He came at me, you know,
like he… like he usually had
and done so many times before.
And for whatever reason,
on this night, I snapped.
I went at him s… screaming
and swinging and next thing I knew,
I slammed the front door
and cursed his name.
Told him I never wanted to see him again.
He then said, "I wish you were dead."
First, it was pride, you know?
Then after a few years,
my life went to shit.
Turned to shame.
A few months ago, I was working
the night shift back in Reno.
And that's when I got the call.
It was my mom.
She said, "You know, Kevin,
your dad's real sick.
You need to come home."
Drove all night.
But I was too late.
He died that morning.
I was too late… as a son.
Now I'm too late as a father.
How many times my son's reached out to me?
And now it's too late.
I didn't show up.
It's not too late.
It's up to you.
- Fire!
Oh, shit.
There's fire.
Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
- Behind us.
- Fire in the back.
There's fire in the back.
I'll be right back.
Kevin!
Kevin! Kevin! Kevin, it's in the back.
It's in the back of the bus.
- There's fire.
- Here. Go, go, go. Okay.
Oh, God.
Miss Mary!
- Where?
Here, here, here, here. Here.
Shit!
It's out. It's out!
It's out. It's out.
- Kevin, we're out.
We're out. It's out.
- The spray.
- Go back to the bus.
Go back to the bus. Go back to the bus!
Where are you going?
- No! No! Kevin!
Shit.
Okay.
Look for fires. Look for fires.
Kevin!
Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
- Come on!
It's behind us.
We gotta drive through it.
Gotta drive through it.
- Sit down, sit down!
What's wrong?
- No.
- Ah! Come on.
- No, no, no, no.
- Come on, come on!
- What? No! No.
Take the wheel.
- Kevin, don't go.
- Come back.
What's Kevin doing?
Try! Try now!
Goddamn it!
- Please, please, please.
Try it! Try now!
- Yes!
Okay! Okay! Okay!
Go! Go, go, go!
Get down. Get down.
We're going through the fire.
Oh, God.
I don't wanna die!
Miss Mary, is it over?
Oh, God.
It's okay. It's okay.
Okay. Okay. We're okay.
Come on through.
This way. This way! Come on!
Come on through. Follow them.
Oh, my God.
- Is that the bus?
- It's them. It's them.
Oh, my God. Oh, my God.
Mom.
Hi!
What are you waiting for? Let's go.
Dad!
Come on, Toby.
Here's your dad. Right here. Right here.
Thirteen, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.
Toby.
Good luck, buddy.
Your mom's right there.
Toby! Toby!
All right.
- Thank you.
You did good. You did really good.
You did too.
Send me a picture of those elephants, huh?
- Mary!
No, no. Your children are amazing.
They were so brave.
Thank you, Mary.
Kevin. Kevin. Kevin.
- Thank you, Kevin.
- Thank you.
Excuse me. Excuse me.
I didn't know if you got my call.
- You okay?
- Yeah.
Hey, boss.
Time for maintenance.
Yeah. I probably owe you
a little overtime too, you know?
All right, now.
- Kevin.
- Hey, sir. Hey, how are you?
Good job. Good job.
All right. Thank you, man.
Sir, I'm sorry…
I'm sorry.
I've got to help the next one, sir.
Ma'am, come up here, please.
Ma'am, what is the name
you're looking for?
- Miller.
Ma'am, there is a Miller.
- Go to the disaster relief tent…
- Where's that?
- …and look for your family, okay?
- They're over there.
- Excuse me.
- Hi, there. Um, McKay.
- What name?
M-C-K-A-Y.
- All right.
- Gonna be a Sherry and Shaun.
They would've come in
from Magalia.
Sir, I'm sorry. I don't see that name.
We'll keep an eye out for them.
Thank you.
Hi, there.
Ma?
- Ma.
- Oh!
Hey. You made it.
How… How'd you get out?
- My neighbor, Carl…
- Carl.
- …he came and got me…
- Carl got you?
- …and brought me here. Yes.
Listen, Ma. Where's Shaun?
Where's Shaun, Ma?
He's with his mother.
He's happiest when he's with her.
He's safe.
It's for the best. Okay?
Yeah.
It is.